<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title type="text">
        Lucas DiCioccio's blog
    </title>
    <id>
        https://dicioccio.fr/atom.xml
    </id>
    <updated>
        2022-12-11T01:00:00Z
    </updated>
    <entry>
        <id>
            https://dicioccio.fr/triangular-decisions.html
        </id>
        <title type="text">
            Understanding decision under constraints with triangular decisions
        </title>
        <updated>
            2023-06-18T01:00:00Z
        </updated>
        <author>
            <name>
                Lucas DiCioccio
            </name>
        </author>
        <content type="html">
            &lt;div class="main-article"&gt;&lt;section class="main-section"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I want to start a series of articles on multi-criteria decisions. Since the topic is broad, I’d like to first write an article about decisions under constraints, starting with &lt;em&gt;triangular tradeoffs&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h1 id="triangular-tradeoffs"&gt;Triangular tradeoffs&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;Triangular tradeoffs are tradeoffs where you lay &lt;em&gt;options&lt;/em&gt; along the sides of a triangle, and you can only pick one corner of the triangle, leaving the opposite side unavailable (it also works if each corner is an option and you need to pick one side). You can construct a triangular trade-off with the template sentence &lt;code&gt;A,B,C - pick two&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Examples of triangular tradeoffs:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Project_management_triangle"&gt;Good, Fast, Cheap&lt;/a&gt; – pick two &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CAP_theorem"&gt;Consistent, Available, Partition-Tolerant&lt;/a&gt; – pick two &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ricardoandlorena.com/lifestyle/money-time-energy"&gt;Energy, Money, Time&lt;/a&gt; – pick two &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://longform.asmartbear.com/docs/fulfillment/"&gt;Joy, Skill, Needs&lt;/a&gt; – pick two &lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;You probably have encountered such sentence because triangular tradeoffs arise in many contexts. The first example is a form of &lt;a href="/hashtags/project-management.html"&gt;&lt;span class="hashtag" data-hashtag="project-management"&gt;#project-management&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; gimmick. The second example is the CAP-Theorem: an impossibility result in computer science. Whereas the two last ones are motivational frameworks to help us go on with our lives.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;These tradeoffs have the same structure about three competing goals that we can place on triangle sides. The next section explains how to thing about triangular tradeoffs.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h1 id="modeling-triangular-tradeoffs"&gt;modeling triangular tradeoffs&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;The most direct representation of triangular tradeoffs is, well, to have a triangle: annotate the sides with the criteria and the &lt;em&gt;decision&lt;/em&gt; is which corner to pick. When picking a corner of a triangle, we actually chose an option which is explicitly characterized along two desireable criteria (e.g., Good and Cheap) while implicitly leaving out the third criteria (i.e., not Fast). Since a triangle has three corners, there are three possible choices. And we can illustrate the three possible choices in the following picture.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/mcd-triangle-01.png" alt="fast good cheap triangle" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;When we draw such a picture, we implicitly hide some information. In the triangle, each &lt;strong&gt;side represents a favorable outcome&lt;/strong&gt; of a decision. Thus, &lt;strong&gt;corner encodes a combination of independant criteria&lt;/strong&gt;. Goodness (Good or not), cost (Cheap or not), and time-to-delivery (Fast or not) are the three independant criteria.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Let’s give a numerical representation to each criteria, say &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt; represents the favorable outcome and &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt; represents the unfavorable outcome. For instance, &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt; is Good, and &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt; is not-Good. With this simple formalims we can then use a three-digit number like &lt;code&gt;011&lt;/code&gt; to represent various positions on the triangle. The first digit (leftmost) encodes cost, the second digit encodes goodness, and the third digit (rightmost) encodes time-to-delivery. Thus &lt;code&gt;101&lt;/code&gt; encodes &lt;code&gt;(Cheap, not-Good, Fast)&lt;/code&gt;. We can now annotate our triangle with these numbers, which is akin to giving a name to each corner:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/mcd-triangle-02.png" alt="fast good cheap triangle, annotated in binary format" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In addition to giving a name to each corner, I’ve also colored each digit and the triangle-side according to the criteria they represent. The picture carries a lot of information: we started saying there are three options to chose from (each corner) and elaborated that we also chose from three criteria (individual digits). Decisions on corners or decisions on digits are inter-related: if we pick one corner we also pick three digits, the converse is true. Thus either way of deciding leads to the same result, but these decisions are different. This story becomes confusing and we are approaching the important lesson of this article. Let’s focus now on what is the relationship between deciding on corners and deciding on digits.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h1 id="corners-or-three-digit-numbers"&gt;corners or three-digit numbers?&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;In triangular decisions, there is some confusion about what we “chose”. Indeed, the decision we make when taking a corner of the triangle is related to (but different from) the decision we make when picking a single digit. Confusion arises due to the fact that, in the latter case, we are &lt;em&gt;deciding under constraints&lt;/em&gt;. Whereas, when picking a corner, the &lt;a href="/hashtags/constraints.html"&gt;&lt;span class="hashtag" data-hashtag="constraints"&gt;#constraints&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; have already been resolved.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;“pick two”&lt;/strong&gt; of the triangular tradeoff template sentence actually is a constraint: we must pick a number &lt;strong&gt;so that the sum of the digits is two&lt;/strong&gt;. In contrast, &lt;strong&gt;“pick a corner”&lt;/strong&gt; is &lt;strong&gt;a shortcut to name configurations&lt;/strong&gt; which happens to have two connected sides: someone (the first human who draw a triangle) already solved the problem “the sum of digits is two” and provided us with a menu of three choices.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Recapitulating: with binary values to represent each of the three possible criteria, we have eight possible configurations. Further, we are given the constraint “pick two”. We formalize this constraint as &lt;code&gt;the sum of the digits is two&lt;/code&gt;. Doing so reduces the triangle tradeoff to “pick a corner” among three configurations. When &lt;a href="/decisions-are-not-outcomes.html"&gt;evaluating decisions&lt;/a&gt; this reduction of the decision space is welcome as we a smaller decision space facilitates the evaluation of a decision. What is important to internalize here is that &lt;strong&gt;the reduction in the number of configurations is not attributed to a “choice”, instead it is the application of constraints&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We can generalize the shortcut-trick to problems having more than three binary criteria. For instance if you are used to playing board game you already know that a tetrahedron can encode “a,b,c,d – pick three” (much like a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Four-sided_die"&gt;four-sided die&lt;/a&gt; picks one out). Thus overall, what we want to study the general framework of applying constraints to reduce the size of a decision space.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h1 id="deciding-under-constraints"&gt;deciding under constraints&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;This section elaborates the general framework of decision under constraints.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Rather than a simple triangular decision, we are given a set of &lt;em&gt;atomic decisions&lt;/em&gt;. These are primitive decisions such as prices, delays, quality, or amounts of sugar cane. We are tasked to &lt;em&gt;decide&lt;/em&gt;. That is, among all the possible &lt;em&gt;configurations&lt;/em&gt;, we need to pick one configuration. Figuratively, we can represent a choice and (a subset of the possible configurations) as follows:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/mcd-choice-reduction-00.png" alt="choice configurations" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In the above picture, we lay down all the small atomic decisions we have to make in gray circles, coloring these decisions means making a choice. Once we color all the circles (which I have not done in the picture because it is fastidious), we have settled on a particular configuration.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;What makes a decision difficult is pairwise. On the first hand, the number of configurations grows exponentially with the number of atomic decisions. On the other hand, evaluating each single decision can cost much effort. Some real-world rules such as physics boundaries, personal preferences, or regulations, reduce the set of decisions we can make.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As the analysis of the triangular tradeoff as shown us, we have two ways to decide:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;either we make choices about one configuration in one-fell swoop &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;or we apply constraints, step back and decide on a reduced set of configurations &lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;The following picture recapitulates these two paths. Top-left, we find our set of atomic decisions. When deciding directly (moving right) we end up with a particular configuration. Whereas we can also first apply some constraint, which means we are left to chose from a reduced set of “bundled” configurations.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/mcd-choice-reduction-01.png" alt="direct choice pick vs choice reduction via constraints" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The distinction between these two decision processes is tenuous: when we decide in one-fell swoop we shall still apply the constraints to arrive to a solution. When we have many constraints, nothing prevents to repeat the process. Indeed, decisions can also take more steps. At each decision step, applying some constraints bundles some configurations from the previous decision-step.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/mcd-choice-reduction-02.png" alt="multi steps reductions" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Other decision-making processes can exist as well if we change slightly the definition of “decision”. For instance, let’s extend the “decision” step with the added power to eliminate at least one-value. That is to say, we can make the decision to do a tiny bit of progress by reducing the set of candidates. Using, this decision repeatedly betweeen applications of some constraints also drive us towards a final decision. Potentially, the final decision happens when a single configuration is left over.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Further, we could extend this process so that a decision step could influence the constraints (e.g., re-ordering them or even creating new ones). Such a technique could allow to capture secondary goals when some condition on the left over combinations happens (e.g., when two options are acceptably performant, consider some risk-threshold before making a by-cost tie-break).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We can illustrate (two steps) of such a process as follows. &lt;img src="/gen/images/mcd-process-01.dot.png" alt="method" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Summarizing, we’ve describes a pretty general decision-making process for decisions under constraints. This process is “recursive” (or fractal and prone to self-references if you prefer): the choice we make when pruning configuration or when picking a constraint for the next step, in itself, is a deicsion. This process is mechanical and deterministic as we can describe it with such graphs. Therefore, if our decision-making process were perfect, &lt;strong&gt;we should end up chosing the same configuration in either path&lt;/strong&gt;. On the opposite, we ultimately make &lt;em&gt;informed-guesses&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;An &lt;a href="/hashtags/informed-guess.html"&gt;&lt;span class="hashtag" data-hashtag="informed-guess"&gt;#informed-guess&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a nice euphemism for instinct-based decisions. There is nothing wrong with such informed-guesses. Indeed, if we annotate the picture from my article about &lt;a href="/decisions-are-not-outcomes.html"&gt;“judging decisions, not outcomes”&lt;/a&gt;, we see that applying constraints to a problem will either reduce the enumeration difficulty or change the evaluation difficulty (e.g., because the constraint pruned some options which required some rare expertise before continuing).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/mcd-choice-reduction-03.png" alt="direct choice pick vs choice reduction via constraints" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Although there is nothing wrong with an informed guess, they are easy to conflate with a rushed decision. In appearance, the shortcut we took in triangular tradeoffs is beneficial because we started from eight configurations and ended up with three configurations. We discarded some solutions subject to related constraints. For instance, admit that “pick at most two” rather than “pick exactly two” is a valid representation of our business case. We then admit more than three solutions (we now have seven solutions). Solutions under the “pick at most two” constraint could be beneficial on other factors that you have not yet accounted for. As a result people tend to challenge solutions with their own interpretation of business rules. Such disagreement can be frustrating. In short, keep in mind that the solution “neither fast, nor cheap, nor good” actually exists and someone, somewhere, may be championing this solution as an alternative to yours. My recommendation against corporate-decisions paralysis is to document decision processed (e.g., via &lt;a href="/talks.html#design-doc-template"&gt;design docs&lt;/a&gt;) so that constraints and evaluation criteria are spelled out.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id="summary-and-conclusion"&gt;Summary and conclusion&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;We discuss the process of deciding under constraints. Starting, from the example of triangular tradeoffs. Such problems asks people to make a pick among three options. These three options actually capture a &lt;em&gt;configuration&lt;/em&gt; among three distinct binary decisions (e.g., good or bad, fast or slow, cheap or expensive). Seemingly we should have to pick among eight configurations. The difference between the two approaches to a same problem is that we applied a constraint (“pick two”) and renamed to three possible configurations.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We then generalize the constraint-application step and sketch a decision-framework of iterative changes to an initial problem. The framework is pretty general and typically the goal is to restrict the number of configurations enough that some instinct-based decision becomes possible. In corporate context, this decision-process is often split among multiple people at various hierarchical ranks.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Real-world decision-making is messy: models capture a biased and sparse vision of reality. Further, our constraint-solving ability is also imperfect: we may misrepresent constraints and economical realities binds us. Ultimately, we make informed guess. In such situation, we need to remember that the final-decision often is an instinct-based decision or frustration will prevail.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/section&gt;&lt;section class="main-section"&gt;&lt;div id="app-err"&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        </content>
        <link href="https://dicioccio.fr/triangular-decisions.html" rel="alternate"/>
        <summary type="text">
            Real-world decisions are tradeoffs under constraints. We like to simplify some tradeoffs with triangular decisions like "cheap, good, fast -- pick two". Let's see what we can learn from these triangles.
        </summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>
            https://dicioccio.fr/decisions-are-not-outcomes.html
        </id>
        <title type="text">
            Decisions are not outcomes
        </title>
        <updated>
            2022-12-11T01:00:00Z
        </updated>
        <author>
            <name>
                Lucas DiCioccio
            </name>
        </author>
        <content type="html">
            &lt;div class="main-article"&gt;&lt;section class="main-section"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Decisions are commodities of our lives: from the second we wake up and until we fall asleep, we are bound to make &lt;a href="/hashtags/decisions.html"&gt;&lt;span class="hashtag" data-hashtag="decisions"&gt;#decisions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to progress during the day. Most decisions we make are inconsequential: which shirt to pick, what flavour of ice cream to eat, and so on and so forth. As a result, we may easily fool ourselves that we are good at making decisions. In practice, gauging whether a decision is good or not is more difficult than it appears. In particular, we tend to conflate good decisions with good &lt;a href="/hashtags/outcomes.html"&gt;&lt;span class="hashtag" data-hashtag="outcomes"&gt;#outcomes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h1 id="decisions-and-situations"&gt;Decisions and situations&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;If we want to improve our decision making, we need to train ourselves to assess the quality of decisions independently from the outcomes of the decisions.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;When we think what making good decisions entails, we often think about decisions that will &lt;em&gt;improve&lt;/em&gt; things. And a common mistake people do when gauging decisions is to gauge the outcome. Indeed, we also make decisions that leave us &lt;em&gt;indifferent&lt;/em&gt;. And, alas, sometimes we need to make the &lt;em&gt;least worst&lt;/em&gt; decision.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Let’s illustrate these three situations with a series of trivial examples. For each example, you have two options: &lt;code&gt;A&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;B&lt;/code&gt; and only one of the option can be chosen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;div class="col3"&gt; &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Situation-1 option-A: - gain $50 option-B: - gain $100 &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt; &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Situation-2 option-A: - gain $100,000,050 option-B: - gain $100,000,100 &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt; &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Situation-3 option-A: - lose $100 option-B: - lose $50 &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;p&gt;In each of the three situations above, &lt;code&gt;option-B&lt;/code&gt; is always more favorable than &lt;code&gt;option-A&lt;/code&gt;. As a result, someone making good decisions would always pick &lt;code&gt;option-B&lt;/code&gt; over &lt;code&gt;option-A&lt;/code&gt;. Furthermore, &lt;code&gt;option-B&lt;/code&gt; is always &lt;code&gt;$50&lt;/code&gt; better than &lt;code&gt;option-A&lt;/code&gt;, somehow, to most people in Situation-2, either options will feel indifferent.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;An important observation in the above example is that any outcome of Situation-2 is preferred over any outcome of Situation-1, which in turn is preferred over any outcome of Situation-3. As a result, a person in Situation-3 taking &lt;code&gt;option-B&lt;/code&gt; makes better decisions than a person in Situation-2 taking &lt;code&gt;option-A&lt;/code&gt;! meanwhile, the person in Situation-2 taking &lt;code&gt;option-A&lt;/code&gt; is in a significantly better place than the person in Situation-3 taking &lt;code&gt;option-B&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The three situations above teach us the following: &lt;em&gt;how-good a decision is independent from how-good an outcome is&lt;/em&gt;. Further, to gauge whether a decision is good or not, one must characterize the set of &lt;em&gt;available options&lt;/em&gt; and then compare options with each other. In short: given a same situation, would you pick the same choice or not? Comparing options differs from comparing &lt;em&gt;unreachable situations&lt;/em&gt; with each other.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h1 id="distinguishing-between-decisions-and-situation-changes"&gt;Distinguishing between decisions and situation-changes&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;The key to distinguish between attainable options and unreachable situations is to understand whether an outcome is too-good-to-be-true &lt;span class="emoji" data-emoji="tm"&gt;™️&lt;/span&gt;. Rational actors would switch to a better situation if they could because &lt;strong&gt;chosing poorly in a good situation results in better outcomes than chosing perfectly in a poor situation&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thus, a first characteristics is that situations define a range of outcomes whereas decisions merely move the needle withing a range of outcomes. Thus, two situation-changing “decisions” are easy to distinguish because there is some boundary (or minimal overlap) between the ranges of achievable outcomes after taking a decision.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For people with a more “visual mind”, we could depict these differences as follows. Three situations (the range &lt;code&gt;[----]&lt;/code&gt;) with a needle (the &lt;code&gt;-o-&lt;/code&gt;). Options would move the needle around whereas situation changes would flip your situation to another row.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; range of possible outcomes |--------------------------------------------------| situation Alpha: [-------------o--------] situation Beta: [--------o-] situation Gamma: [o--------------] &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt; &lt;p&gt;The ranges in the example above characterize different &lt;a href="/hashtags/situations.html"&gt;&lt;span class="hashtag" data-hashtag="situations"&gt;#situations&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: the available choices for routine decisions are close to each other and result in marginal changes of outcome. Thus, hypotetically, after taking a first option and re-assessing the situation: would your routine decisions (for which you are mostly indifferent) fall on a similar continuum as if you had taken another option first? If you answer yes, the option you are assessing is a situation-changing option.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="emoji" data-emoji="exclamation"&gt;❗&lt;/span&gt; Note, if you are a manager of technical people, suggesting that switching situations is a mere decition will cross your interlocutor because hypothesizing unrealistic options implies an obvious situation-changing choice is not being made (i.e., it implies that your interlocutor is stupid). Questions like “&lt;strong&gt;why don’t you just&lt;/strong&gt; replace system-XYZ” will be received as a sort of “stop-being-poor” insult or as intellectual-laziness. Not be the brainstorm-session ice-breaker you hoped for.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Alas, lines are often blurry. In business settings especially, situations that are unreachable to one may be reachable at an upper management echelon. In particular, the role of strategy is to put you in good situations, whereas the role of tactics is to make good decisions within your current situation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Some business-settings examples of decisions among available options could be:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;hire a new employee or keep on course &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;implement a piece of logic inside the DB or in the controller or in the model or in the view &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;build anew or maintain a system &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;should I investigate an issue by looking at changes or looking at logs or doing some reproduction checks &lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;Some situation-changing decisions between unreachable (to most except C-suite people) situations could be:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;stop paying for mission-critical systems to build in house &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;replace the whole team or keep on course &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;stop or not a money-making business-line with low profit-margins &lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;In my experience, people mixing available options and unreachable situations happens on a regular basis. Probably not in extreme cases like my example above, where people recognize that transitory situations will exist. Making realistic plans require hard work to draw a picture of how a company could move from one situation to another one.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h1 id="making-better-decisions"&gt;Making better decisions&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;Now we understand that a situation constrains the set of choices one can make. Within this set of choice, then we still want to make good decisions.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;To make good decisions you need to start with enumerating available options, and enumerating and evaluating options is almost all there is to good-decisions making. Alas the enumeration itself can take too long or the evaluation may fall short due to lack of information.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;If we draw these two dimensions on a board, we can split decision-making in four broad quadrants.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/weighing-decisions-quadrants.png" alt="decision quadrants along evaluation difficulty and enumeration difficulty axes" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Bottom-left are “easy decisions”: in these cases, intuitive choices are good enough. You can easily convince yourself which option is better and people coming after you gauging and revisiting your choices with hindsight will easily realize you were right.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Top-left are high-cost decisions that are amenable to scrutinization. Many (software) engineering situations fall in this quadrant: choices are few but evaluation is difficult. In this quadrant, I recommend to use evaluation matrices and other tools like design docs (you’ll find a template on the &lt;a href="/talks.html"&gt;talks-and-docs page&lt;/a&gt;) to formalize &lt;strong&gt;and record&lt;/strong&gt; how decisions were made.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Bottom-right are low-cost but numerous decisions. These choice happen when a seemingly-single choice actually consists of a combination of choices and where evaluation can be automated without too much guesswork. &lt;a href="/topics/optimization.html"&gt;optimizations frameworks&lt;/a&gt; allows to enumerate and compare choices efficiently. For these techniques to work on needs to restrict the decisions to some formal and limited model of our reality.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Finally, in the difficult top-right quadrant, you may not be able to make a good decisions. The only reassuring thing is that if you cannot devise a good choice, your competitors likely are in a similar situation. In such a situation what is key is to understand the range of outcomes in best/worst/average situations, and assessing whether investing efforts in better decisions is offset by the outcome. Thus, you need some preliminary investigation to justify whether rolling a dice is an okay-move or not. If high-stakes are at play (that is if the range of outcomes are such that making a good decision is actually critical), I’d say that the best thing to do is to seek help from people with modeling, simulation, and/or scientific-experiments experience.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h1 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;Decisions are choices in a set of options. Circumstances from your situation determine the set of options available to you. Empathize with people (including your past self) to disambiguate situations having poor outcomes from poor decisions. What is key is: given the same input and the same situation, would I still chose the same option?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In business settings, be careful to distinguish when decisions are tactical (i.e., trying to improve the outcome by making some choices) from when decisions are strategical (i.e., trying to improve the outcome by changing the range of choices). When the strategy attempts such a transformation, often what is amiss is a picture to move smoothly between two disconnected situations.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;When deciding within options, your decision-making quality is a direct output of how thorough is your assessment of the set of available options (the enumeration) and your assessment of how good are options (the evaluation). Once you have these, making a good decision is a matter of ranking among choices. Keep in mind that analyzing choices has a cost, and the effort made to enumerate and rank choices should be smaller than the difference in outcomes between good and bad decisions. To help during this process, you should rely on decision frameworks like design-docs and mathematical modeling. Experts can help you with these.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I hope that, in retrospect, you’ll think that reading this article was a good decision &lt;span class="emoji" data-emoji="grimacing"&gt;😬&lt;/span&gt;. Have a good day!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        </content>
        <link href="https://dicioccio.fr/decisions-are-not-outcomes.html" rel="alternate"/>
        <summary type="text">
            Deciding is difficult, we always want to improve our decision making. What's more or at least as difficult? gauging whether a decision is good or not.
        </summary>
    </entry>
</feed>
